<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Object_List>
<Display_Attributes>Date,Materials,Weight,Region</Display_Attributes>
<Object>
<Title>Corinthian helmet</Title>
<Date>About 550 BCE</Date>
<Materials>Russeted iron with gilding</Materials>
<Weight>5 lb. 9 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Possibly from the Greek colonies in Southern France</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.7</Credit>
<Description>
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.
</Description>
<ID>20147</ID>
<Picture>2014.7.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>44.8</Latitude>
<Longitude>2.2</Longitude>
<Country>FR</Country>
</Object>

<Object>
<Title>Corinthian helmet</Title>
<Date>550-450 BCE</Date>
<Materials>Bronze</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 4 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Greece</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.30</Credit>
<Description>Originally a bright gold color, the bronze has turned green over time. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet was worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he wore torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear, the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.</Description>
<ID>201430</ID>
<Picture>2014.30.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>39</Latitude>
<Longitude>22</Longitude>
<Country>GR</Country>
</Object>

<Object>
<Title>Montefortino helmet</Title>
<Date>About 400-200 BCE</Date>
<Materials>Bronze, iron</Materials>
<Weight>4 lb. 4 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Italian Peninsula</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.22</Credit>
<Description>The Montefortino helmet style originated among the Celtic people of Gaul (present-day France). Tribes of Celts invaded Italy after 400 B.C.E. and sacked Rome around 390.  Native Italians were quick to adopt the military styles of the conquerors. By the time of the Punic Wars against Carthage in the 200s, the Montefortino helmet had become standard equipment for soldiers of the Roman republic.  The fine workmanship and delicate decoration suggest it is an early example of the Montefortino style, but it is impossible to determine whether it was made by a Celt, Roman, or Etruscan.</Description>
<ID>201422</ID>
<Picture>2014.22.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>41</Latitude>
<Longitude>15.5</Longitude>
<Country>IT</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Helmet</Title>
<Date>Possibly 1500s, modified in 1800s</Date>
<Materials>Russeted iron with gilding</Materials>
<Weight>5 lb. 9 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Originally Turkey, modified in Sudanic region, northern Africa</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.91</Credit>
<Description>This well-traveled helmet had a working life that spanned many centuries. Originally made for a high-ranking nobleman in the Ottoman Empire, much of its original gilded surface is still visible. However, the arrow-shaped noseguard was made much later in the Sudanic region, just south of the Sahara desert in Africa. Over the years, the Ottoman Empire abandoned its traditional arms and armor in favor of equipment used by European armies. This helmet was sold off as military surplus, eventually finding its way across the Sahara to a region where older styles of Islamic arms were still in use.</Description>
<ID>201491</ID>
<Picture>2014.91.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>39</Latitude>
<Longitude>33</Longitude>
<Country>TR</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Missyurka</Title>
<Date>1500s-1600s</Date>
<Materials>Iron</Materials>
<Weight>2 lb. 2 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Turkey or Caucasus</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.102</Credit>
<Description>The missyurka were used by horsemen throughout the Ottoman Empire as well as in areas influenced by Ottoman culture, including Eastern Europe, Russia, and the Caucasus. The defense was worn high on the head, over a cap or fez, and might be wrapped with a turban around its base. </Description>
<ID>2014102</ID>
<Picture>2014.102.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>39</Latitude>
<Longitude>38</Longitude>
<Country>TR</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Close-helmet for the Field</Title>
<Date>About 1535-1540</Date>
<Materials>Fire-blued steel with gilding, embossing, and incised decoration</Materials>
<Weight>8 lb. 3 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Possibly Caremolo Modrone (Italian, Mantua, 1498-1543)</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.11</Credit>
<Description>This splendid helmet is apparently the only surviving element from a very fine armor, similar to a suit made as a gift for Holy Roman Emperor Charles V. The surface has been left hammer-rough, retaining the hand-forged surface. Usually, a succession of lighter hammers was used to smooth out the steel, which ultimately was then polished. In this example, however, the armorer has left the surface rough for an exquisite effect, emphasized by a heat-treatment that darkened the color and embossed decoration accented in gold.</Description>
<ID>201411</ID>
<Picture>2014.11.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>43.2</Latitude>
<Longitude>12</Longitude>
<Country>IT</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Shishak</Title>
<Date>1550-1600</Date>
<Materials>Steel, iron, brass, fabric</Materials>
<Weight>5 lb. 3 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Probably Russia, Moscow</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.72</Credit>
<Description>A tall central spire or spike is a common feature of Islamic helmets. This particular style is found in Persian, Turkish, and Russian helmets, reflecting the cultural interchange among these areas at the borders of Europe and Asia. The peak at the front is a particularly Turkish feature, reflecting the cultural impact of the Ottomans in Eastern Europe at the height of their empire in the 1500s.</Description>
<ID>201472</ID>
<Picture>2014.72.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>63</Latitude>
<Longitude>93</Longitude>
<Country>RU</Country>
</Object>



<Object>
<Title>Morion-burgonet</Title>
<Date>1585</Date>
<Materials>Blackened and fire-gilt etched steel, brass</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 10 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Southern Germany, probably Augsburg</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.26</Credit>
<Description>This helmet was probably worn by a bodyguard to a noble family. The form is Italian in origin, but was also popular in Austria, Germany, and France during the second half of the 1500s. The stylized curves imitate helmets that Renaissance artists imagined on the heads of ancient Greek and Roman warriors. </Description>
<ID>201426</ID>
<Picture>2014.26.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>49.5</Latitude>
<Longitude>10</Longitude>
<Country>DE</Country>
</Object>



<Object>
<Title>Comb morion for the guard of Christian I or II, Electors of Saxony</Title>
<Date>Probably around 1590</Date>
<Materials>Blackened steel with etched and gilded decoration, brass, leather</Materials>
<Weight>4 lb.</Weight>
<Region>Germany, Nuremberg</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.48</Credit>
<Description>The dukes of Saxony were powerful German princes who maintained a personal bodyguard unit of over 200 horsemen and footsoldiers. This helmet was made specifically for these troops. The bodyguards’ uniforms were black with gold decoration, reflecting the heraldic colors of the duke’s coat-of-arms, and the helmet was made to match. 
The guard equipment was later displayed in a special gallery of the ducal armory in the Dresden, the Saxon capital. From the 1800s onward, much of the equipment was given away or sold. In the 1830s, numerous comb morions such this one were sent to the city’s opera house as props.</Description>
<ID>201448</ID>
<Picture>2014.48.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>52.5</Latitude>
<Longitude>12</Longitude>
<Country>DE</Country>
</Object>





<Object>
<Title>Kulah khud</Title>
<Date>Probably 1600s</Date>
<Materials>Iron, silver, gold</Materials>
<Weight>2 lb. 12 oz.</Weight>
<Region>India</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.88</Credit>
<Description>When the Mughals invaded northern India around 1500, they brought with them the artistic traditions of Islamic Persia, including arms and armor. The kulah khud is the most common type of Persian helmet, one of many variants of the Islamic form with rounded skull, top spike, and mail neck-guard. However, the embossed pattern on the helmet-bowl recalls the lotus flower, which is more typical of Indian designs. </Description>
<ID>201488</ID>
<Picture>2014.88.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>22</Latitude>
<Longitude>78.5</Longitude>
<Country>IN</Country>
</Object>

<Object>
<Title>Helmet in the form of a sea conch shell</Title>
<Date>1618</Date>
<Materials>Iron with traces of lacquer, textiles</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 13 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Nagasone Tojiro Mitsumasa (Japanese, Nagasone School, Echizen Province)</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.89</Credit>
<Description>Modern soldiers wear camouflage in order to avoid being seen. In feudal Japan, military leaders went to great lengths to get noticed. As armies grew and samurai wore increasingly fine armor, top-level commanders took to wearing outlandish helmets to set themselves apart.  This helmet was probably inspired by the riveted plates of medieval Japanese helmets, but the conical rivet-heads have morphed into the elegant spikes of a conch shell. We don’t know who owned this remarkable work, but it must have graced the head of one of the most important men in Japan. It was so admired that several imitations were made during the 1600s.  The conch has diverse meanings in Japan, an island where the inhabitants are never far from the sea. The shell symbolized military authority, carried by Japanese commanders as a battle-horn. But the sound of the conch shell also represented the preaching of Buddhist enlightenment.</Description>
<ID>201489</ID>
<Picture>2014.89.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>36</Latitude>
<Longitude>138</Longitude>
<Country>JP</Country>
</Object>





<Object>
<Title>Kulah khud</Title>
<Date>Possibly 1700s, altered in 1800s</Date>
<Materials>Iron, gold and silver inlay</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 8 oz.</Weight>
<Region>Persia</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.71</Credit>
<Description>The kulah khud is the traditional helmet of Persia. The style remained in ceremonial use long after it had ceased to have any military function. This piece appears to have been altered in the 1800s, with the insertion of a small horned head between the helmet bowl and its surmounting spike. The modification may have served to convert the helmet for use in a Shi’ite religious play. </Description>
<ID>201471</ID>
<Picture>2014.71.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>32</Latitude>
<Longitude>55</Longitude>
<Country>IR</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Helmet</Title>
<Date>About 1800</Date>
<Materials>Steel, brass, copper</Materials>
<Weight>2 lb.</Weight>
<Region>Probably China</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.43</Credit>
<Description>When the Mongol empire spread across Asia in the 1200s, it created a vast political and economic network that fostered cultural interchange for centuries to come. Helmets similar to this can be found in Mongolia, China, and Korea, but the closest parallels appear to be Chinese infantry helmets from around 1800. This particular example is fairly plain, suggesting that it belonged to an ordinary footsoldier. The finial at the top once held a tube for a horsehair plume. The brim originated in the Islamic Middle East, and was imported across the Mongol trade routes to East Asia. The paired holes around the lower edge once held a padded fabric neck-guard.</Description>
<ID>201443</ID>
<Picture>2014.43.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>35</Latitude>
<Longitude>105</Longitude>
<Country>CN</Country>
</Object><Object>
<Title>Helmet for a carabineer</Title>
<Date>1863-1865</Date>
<Materials>Steel with brass, leather, horsehair</Materials>
<Weight>N/A</Weight>
<Region>Châtellerault Arsenal (France, Alsace)</Region>
<Credit>The John Woodman Higgins Collection, 2014.90.1</Credit>
<Description>Although armor lost its military importance by the late 1600s, it never entirely vanished. In the 1800s, head and body armor was still used in battle by heavy cavalry. Although ultimately derived from the armor of the medieval knight, this helmet also echoes the classical styles of ancient Rome.  As late as World War I, troopers headed off to the front wearing comparable armor. Such armor was quickly abandoned in the face of machine guns and trench warfare, at the same moment that modern helmets came into use. Today, this older style of armor is still worn by a few elite military units in Europe on ceremonial occasions.</Description>
<ID>201490.1</ID>
<Picture>2014.90.1.jpg</Picture>
<Latitude>48</Latitude>
<Longitude>2.8</Longitude>
<Country>FR</Country>
</Object>
</Object_List>
