<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<objects_list>
<object>
<Title>3050 Sudanic helmet</Title>
<Region>Originated from Ottoman Empire, modified in Sudanic Region, North Africa</Region>
	
	
<Date>
	1500s, modified in 1800s
	</Date>
<Artifact_type>Helmet</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Russeted iron with gilding</Materials>
<Weight>5 lb. 9 oz.</Weight>
<Id>1135</Id>
<Extended_label>This well travelled helmet had a working life that spanned many centuries. It was originally made for a high-ranking nobleman in the Ottoman Empire—you can still see much of its original gilded surface. But the arrow-shaped noseguard was made much later, and is typical of the Sudanic region, just south of the Sahara desert in Africa. Over the years, the Ottoman Empire abandoned its traditional arms and armor in favor of the equipment used by European armies. This helmet was sold off as “military surplus,” eventually finding its way across the Sahara to a region where the older styles of Islamic arms were still in use.</Extended_label>
<Picture>1135.jpg</Picture><lat>63</lat><Lng>93</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>2973 Conch shell helmet</Title>
<Region>Japan</Region>
<Date>1618</Date>
<Artifact_type>Helmet in the form of a sea conch shell</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Iron with traces of lacquer</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 13 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>c9" H x 10.5" D x 12" W</Dimensions>
<Id>2973</Id>
<Extended_label>Nowadays, soldiers wear camouflage in order to avoid being seen. In feudal Japan, military leaders went to great lengths to get noticed. As armies grew and samurai wore increasingly fine armor, top-level commanders took to wearing outlandish helmets to set themselves apart.</Extended_label>
<Picture>2973.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>46.5</lat><Lng>22</Lng>
	
</object>

<object>
<Title>239 Corinthian helmet</Title>
<Region>Possibly from the Greek colonies in southern France</Region>
<Date>About 550 B.C.</Date>
<Artifact_type>"Corinthian" helmet</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Bronze</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 10 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>8" H x 7 1/2" W x 10 1/2" D</Dimensions>
<Id>239</Id>
<Extended_label>This simple yet elegant helmet dates to the early part of the Greek classical age. The bronze has turned green with time; it was originally a bright gold color. The holes around the edge served to attach a padded lining. This helmet would have been worn by a hoplite, a heavily armed footsoldier fighting in massed formations. In addition to the helmet, he would have torso armor of bronze or layered cloth, a large round shield, and a spear. In Classical Greek art, this is the kind of armor worn by the legendary heroes of the Trojan War.</Extended_label>
<Picture>239.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>43.2</lat>
	<Lng>12</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>416 Close helmet</Title>
<Region>Italy (Mantua)</Region>
<Date>About 1535-40</Date>
<Artifact_type>Close-helmet for the field</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Fire-blued steel with gilding, embossing, and incised decoration</Materials>
<Weight>8 lb. 3 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>31.8cm X 27.0cm X 34.0cm D</Dimensions>
<Id>416</Id>
<Extended_label>This splendid helmet is apparently the only surviving element from what must have been a very fine armor, similar in style to a suit made as a gift for Holy Roman Emperor Charles V. The surface has been left hammer-rough, retaining the hand-forged surface. Normally a succession of lighter hammers would be used to smooth out the steel, and ultimately it would be ground, buffed, and polished mirror-bright. But here the armorer has left the surface rough for an exquisite esthetic effect, emphasized by heat-treatment that darkened the color, and with embossed decoration highlighted by gold accents.</Extended_label>
<Picture>416.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>52.3</lat>
	<Lng>11.8</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>1135 Montefortino helmet</Title>
<Region>Italian Peninsula</Region>
<Date>About 400-200 B.C.</Date>
<Artifact_type>Type A "Montefortino" helmet</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Bronze; iron</Materials>
<Weight>4 lb. 4 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>(H) 7 1/2" x (W) 7 5/8" x (D) skull 8 5/8"</Dimensions>
<Id>1135</Id>
<Extended_label>The Montefortino style of helmet originated among the Celtic people of Gaul (modern France). Tribes of Celts invaded Italy after 400 B.C.E., sacking Rome around 390. </Extended_label>
<Picture>1135.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>41</lat>
	<Lng>15.5</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>1191 Morion-burgonet</Title>
<Region>Southern Germany (probably Augsburg)</Region>
<Date>1585</Date>
<Artifact_type>Morion-burgonet</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Etched steel, blackened and fire-gilt; brass</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 10 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>L. 39.9 cm. x W. 23.1 cm. x H 25.5 cm</Dimensions>
<Id>1191</Id>
<Extended_label>This helmet was probably worn by a bodyguard to a noble family. The form is Italian in origin, but was also popular in Austria, Germany and France during the second half of the 1500s. The stylized curves on this example imitate helmets that Renaissance artists imagined on the heads of ancient Greek and Roman warriors. An almost identical helmet in the Art Institute of Chicago also bears the date 1585, as found here on a small, curving band at the front end of the comb.</Extended_label>
<Picture>1191.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>38.5</lat>
	<Lng>22</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>1998.01 Dresden helmet</Title>
<Region> Germany (Nuremberg)</Region>
<Date>Probably around 1590</Date>
<Artifact_type>Comb morion for the guard of Christian I or II, Electors of Saxony</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Blackened steel with etched and gilded decoration; brass; leather</Materials>
<Weight>4 lb.</Weight>
<Dimensions>H 11" x L 14 1/16" x W 9 5/8"</Dimensions>
<Id>1998.01</Id>
<Extended_label>The dukes of Saxony were powerful German princes who maintained a personal bodyguard unit (Trabantengarde) numbering some 200 horsemen and footsoldiers. This helmet was specifically made for these troops. The bodyguards’ uniforms were black with gold decoration, reflecting the heraldic colors of the duke’s coat-of-arms, and the helmet is made to match.</Extended_label>
<Picture>1998.01.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>36</lat>
	<Lng>128</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>2553 Kulah khud</Title>
<Region>Persia</Region>
<Date>Perhaps 1700s, altered in 1800s</Date>
<Artifact_type>Kulah khud (helmet)</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Iron; gold and silver inlay</Materials>
<Weight>3 lb. 8 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions></Dimensions>
<Id>2553</Id>
<Extended_label>The kulah khud is the characteristic helmet of Persia, and remained in ceremonial use long after it had ceased to have any military function. This piece seems to have been altered in the 1800s, to insert the small horned head between the helmet bowl and its surmounting spike. The modification may have been to convert the helmet for use in a Shi’ite religious play. The mail on this helmet is of outstandingly fine riveted links, typically an indication of an old piece.</Extended_label>
	
	<Picture>2553.jpg</Picture><lat>49.5</lat>
	<Lng>10</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>3007.1 Carabinier armor helmet</Title>
<Region></Region>
<Date></Date>
<Artifact_type></Artifact_type>
<Materials></Materials>
<Weight></Weight>
<Dimensions></Dimensions>
<Id>3007.1</Id>
<Extended_label>Although armor had lost its military importance by the late 1600s, it never entirely vanished. In the 1800s, helmets and torso armor like this were still used in battle by heavy cavalry. Though ultimately derived from the armor of the medieval knight, this armor is redesigned to echo the classical styles of ancient Rome. </Extended_label>
<Picture>3007.1.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>33</lat>
	<Lng>54</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>NN.228 Missyurka</Title>
<Region>Ottoman Empire or Caucasus</Region>
<Date>1500s-1600s</Date>
<Artifact_type>Missyurka (skull cap)</Artifact_type>
<Materials></Materials>
<Weight>2 lb. 2 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions></Dimensions>
<Id>nn.228</Id>
<Extended_label>This missyurka, with its round dome, attached neck-guard of mail, and top spike, is one variant of a typically Islamic style of helmet. The ear-flaps are unusual, and their fit into the mail is slightly awkward, suggesting that they may be a working-life modification—possibly cannibalized from another helmet to be added to this one. Versions of the missyurka, usually without ear-flaps and with a longer neck-guard, were used by horsemen throughout the Ottoman Empire as well as areas influenced by Ottoman culture, including eastern Europe, Russia, and the Caucasus. The defense was worn high on the head, over a cap or fez, and might be wrapped with a turban around its base. In remote areas of the Caucasus the missyurka continued in use into the late 1800s.</Extended_label>
<Picture>nn.228.jpg</Picture>
	<lat>22</lat>
	<Lng>78.5</Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>2971.2 Indian kulah khud</Title>
<Region>India</Region>
<Date>Probably 1600s</Date>
<Artifact_type>Kulah khud (helmet)</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Iron; silver; gold</Materials>
<Weight>2 lb. 12 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions></Dimensions>
<Id>2971.2</Id>
<Extended_label>When the Mughals invaded northern India around 1500, they brought with them the artistic traditions of Islamic Persia, including Persian arms and armor. The kulah khud is the most common type of Persian helmet, one of many variants of the widespread Islamic form with rounded skull, top spike, and mail neck-guard. But the embossed pattern on the helmet-bowl, reminiscent of the lotus flower, is typically Indian. This is only one of many Indian variants on the Persian kulah khud.</Extended_label>
<Picture>2971.2.jpg</Picture>
	<lat></lat>
	<Lng></Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>2558 Shishak</Title>
<Region>Probably Russia (perhaps Moscow)</Region>
<Date>1550-1600</Date>
<Artifact_type>Shishak</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Steel; iron; brass; fabric</Materials>
<Weight>5 lb. 3 oz.</Weight>
<Dimensions>36.4cm O.H; cheekpieces: 14.3Hx12.8W(R); 14.4Hx13.0W(L); diameter at base of skull: 21.2</Dimensions>
<Id>2558</Id>
<Extended_label>A tall central spire or spike is a common feature of Islamic helmets, with many variants in regions influenced by Islamic culture. This particular style is found in Persian, Turkish, and Russian helmets, reflecting the cultural interchange between these three areas at the borders of Europe and Asia. The peak at the front is a particularly Turkish feature, reflecting the cultural influence of the Ottomans in Eastern Europe at the height of their empire in the 1500s.</Extended_label>
<Picture>2558.jpg</Picture>
	<lat></lat>
	<Lng></Lng>
</object>

<object>
<Title>1903 East Asian helmet</Title>
<Region>Probably Korea</Region>
<Date>Perhaps 1700s</Date>
<Artifact_type>Helmet</Artifact_type>
<Materials>Steel; brass; copper</Materials>
<Weight> 2 lb.</Weight>
<Dimensions></Dimensions>
<Id>1903</Id>
<Extended_label>When the Mongol empire spread across Asia in the 1200s, it created a vast political and economic network that fostered cultural interchange for centuries to come. Helmets similar to this can be found in Mongolia, China, and Korea, but the closest parallels appear to be Chinese infantry helmets from around 1800—this particular example is fairly plain, suggesting that it was made for an ordinary footsoldier. The finial at the top once held a tube for a horsehair plume. The brim at the front is a feature that originated in the Islamic Middle East, and was imported across the Mongol trade routes to East Asia. The paired holes around the lower edge once held a padded fabric neck-guard.</Extended_label>
<Picture>1903.jpg</Picture>
	<lat></lat>
	<Lng></Lng>
</object>
</objects_list>
